A Finding Aid to the Managing Editor Russell Lynes Correspondence with Artists, 1946-1965, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Managing editor Russell Lynes correspondence with artists
1946-1965
Archives of American Art
Lynes, Russell, 1910-1991
AAA.harpmaga
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
Correspondence with artists kept by Russell Lynes in his capacity as managing editor of Harper's Magazine, measures one linear foot and dates from 1946 to 1965. The files consist primarily of correspondence with young artists and illustrators wishing to submit material to the magazine. Biographical notes from the magazine's "Personal and Otherwise" column about the artists whose material was accepted, clippings, scattered original artwork, and printed reproductions of artwork, are also included.
Arrangement
Records are arranged as one series due to the small size of the collection.
Series 1: Managing Editor Russell Lynes Correspondence with Artists, 1946-1965 (1 linear foot; Box 1)
Biographical / Historical
Russell Lynes (1910-1991) joined Harper's Magazine as an assistant editor in 1944, and served as managing editor from 1947-1967. As an essayist, social historian, photographer, and arbiter of taste, Lynes served informally as art editor and corresponded with many artists regarding submissions to the magazine.
In addition to gaining renown for the thoughtful articles published in Harper's under his stewardship, Lynes was known for his satirical commentary on American tastes and preferences, particularly in architecture and decoration, in such books as Highbrow, Lowbrow, Middlebrow (1949), The Tastemakers (1954), and later works including The Art-Makers of Nineteenth Century America (1970).
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 1967 by Harper & Row via Russell Lynes.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence with artists kept by Russell Lynes in his capacity as managing editor of Harper's Magazine, measures one linear foot and dates from 1946 to 1965. The files consist primarily of correspondence with young artists and illustrators wishing to submit material to the magazine. Biographical notes from the magazine's "Personal and Otherwise" column about the artists whose material was accepted, clippings, scattered original artwork, and printed reproductions of artwork, are also included.
Although brief, the exchanges found in this collection offer a glimpse into the early careers of the artists represented, who often penned introductions to their work, and provided biographical information. Some of the letters are illustrated. Artists represented include Edmond Amateis, Benny Andrews, Irene Aronson, Oscar Berger, Marvin Bileck, Isabel Bishop, Carlyle Brown, Claire Burch, Ivan Chermayeff, Richard E. Davis, Robert J. Day, Eldon Dedini, Harvey Dinnerstein, Dean Ellis, Joseph Farris, Helen Frank, Frank Gallo, William D. Gorman, Douglas W. Gorsline, William Gropper, John Groth, Albert Hirschfeld, Carl Holty, Anne M. Jauss, Hans Jelinek, Kay Kato, Ted Key, Bernard Krigstein, Joseph Low, Loren MacIver, Jack Markow, Reginald Marsh, Charles E. Martin, William Mauldin, Richard Mayhew, Edward Melcarth, Glen Michaels, Nicolas Mordvinoff, Robert Osborn, David Pascal, Bernard Perlin, Ben Shahn, Bernarda Bryson Shahn, Aaron Sopher, Saul Steinberg, Susanne Suba, Peter Takal, Tony Walton, Andy Warhol, and Robert J. Wolff.
In addition to correspondence with artists there are notes on telephone calls to artists used for updating information in the Harper's Magazine files, reference letters written by Lynes on behalf of some artists, correspondence and memoranda with others regarding publishing logistics, and printed material featuring artwork.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels D360 and 4961 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Magazine illustration; Illustrators; Illustrated letters; Berger, Oscar, 1901-1997; Osborn, Robert Chesley, 1904-1994; Perlin, Bernard, 1918-; Shahn, Ben, 1898-1969; Bryson, Bernarda; Warhol, Andy, 1928-
- Managing Editor Russell Lynes Correspondence with Artists, 1946-1965; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and chronologically thereafter. Individuals for whom there are five or more letters have named files; other correspondents are in general files by letter.
  Scope and Contents
  Although brief, the exchanges found in this collection offer a glimpse into the early careers of the artists represented, who often penned introductions to their work and provided biographical information. in addition to correspondence with artists there are on telephone calls to artists, reference letters written by Lynes, and printed material featuring artwork.
  The Andy Warhol file relates to his work as an illustrator for John Cheever's "Vega" and other stories. Included are a letter with an ink sketch from Warhol, 1949, presumably in response to a request for biographical information: "...my life couldn't fill a penny postcard...i graduated from Carnegie Tech now i'm in NY city moving from one roach infested apartment to another"; a postcard to Frances Lattman, 1952, asking her to thank Lynes for letting him draw pictures for Shirley Jackson's stories and mentioning the possibility of a show of his drawings influenced by Truman Capote; an exhibition announcement for his Capote drawings at the Hugo Gallery; and three clippings from Harper's Magazine about Warhol, 1949-1952.
  - Anderson, Donald, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Attie, David, circa 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A, General, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Banbery, Frederick E., circa 1953-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barlow, Perry, 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bates, Bill, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berg, Joan Phyllis, circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Berger, Oscar, circa 1947-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Birmingham-Southern College, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Block, Lou, 1948-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bodecker, Max, 1957-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bryson-Shahn, Bernada, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Burris, Burrah, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ba-Bi, General, 1946-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bi-Bu, General, 1947-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Canton, Shelly Terman, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cato, Robert, 1951-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Collins, Bob, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - C, General, 1947-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Diamond, Harry O, circa 1951-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Donohue, Paula, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - D, General, 1946-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Evans, Walker, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - E, General, 1952-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fabrès, Oscar, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Farris, Joseph G., 1950-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ffeiffer, Jules, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fisher, Ed, 1958-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Forte, Joseph, circa 1952-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - F, General, 1949-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gillespie, George E., 1955-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Goldblatt, Burt, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gorman, William D., 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Groth, John, 1949-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ga-Go, 1950-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gr-Gu, 1947-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hershfield, Leo, 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - H, General, 1949-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - I-J, General, 1946-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Katt, Elliot M., 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Kelley, Mark E., Jr., 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Key, Ted, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Kinnell, Galway, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Kruse, Jürgen, 1958-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Kuskin, Karla, 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - K, General, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Lloyd, Peggy, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - L, General, 1951-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Martin, Charles E., 1949-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Martin, Charles F., 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - McCallister, Richard, 1957-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - McMahon, Franklin, 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Melcarth, Edward, 1949-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - M.-Mar, General, 1947-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Mau-Mi, General, 1950-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Mo-Mu, General, 1947-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - N, General, 1949-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Osborn, Robert, circa 1958-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - O, General, 1951-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Powers, Matthew L., Jr., 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Perlin, Bernard, 1947-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - P, General, 1953-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - R, General, 1951-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Sens, A. G., 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Shahn, Ben, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Shilstone, Arthur, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Smith, Robert B., 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Sokol, Erich, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Sopher, Aaron, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Sa-So, General, 1947-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Sp-Sw, General, 1948-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Taber, Eileen, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - T, General, 1952-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - U-V, General, 1949-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Wadsworth, Charles, circa 1954-circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Warhol, Andy, 1949-circa 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - White, Anne, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - White, David Omar, circa 1958-circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Whitlock, Walter C., 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - W-Y, General, 1949-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1950-circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Printed Material, circa 1950-circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 82)